Adam Ockelford: I promise there won't be too much
آدم أوكلفورد: أعدكم بأني لن أتكلم كثيرا
of me talking, and a lot of Derek playing,
وسنترك مجالا أكبر لسماع عزف دِيرِيكْ،
but I thought it would just be nice to recap
لكني ارتأيت أنه من الجميل تقديم لمحة
on how Derek got to where he is today.
حول كيفية بلوغ دِيرِيكْ لما هو عليه اليوم.
It's amazing now, because he's so much bigger than me,
هذا مدهش، لأن حجمه اليوم أكبر مني بكثير،
but when Derek was born,
لكن عند ولادته،
he could have fitted on the palm of your hand.
كان دِيرِيكْ بحجم راحة اليد.
He was born three and a half months premature,
فقد ولد 3 أشهر ونصف سابق لأوانه،
and really it was a fantastic fight for him to survive.
وقد كانت بالفعل معركة مدهشة خاضها للبقاء.
He had to have a lot of oxygen,
كان بحاجة ماسة للكثير من الأوكسجين،
and that affected your eyes, Derek,
وقد أثر ذلك على بصرك، دِيرِيكْ،
and also the way you understand language
وعلى طريقتك في فهم الكلام
and the way you understand the world.
والعالم من حولك.
But that was the end of the bad news,
لكن هذا كان نهاية الأخبار السيئة،
because when Derek came home from the hospital,
لأنه بعودة دِيرِيكْ من المشفى،
his family decided to employ the redoubtable nanny
قررت أسرته توظيف الحاضنة (المخيفة)
who was going to look after you, Derek,
التي كانت ستهتم بك، يا دِيرِيكْ،
really for the rest of your childhood.
وذلك خلال طفولتك.
And Nanny's great insight, really,
والحقيقة، بفضل بصيرة الحاضنة
was to think, here's a child who can't see.
التي فكرت بأن هذا طفل ضرير.
Music must be the thing for Derek.
وأن الموسيقى هي المجال الملائم لدِيرِيكْ.
And sure enough, she sang, or as Derek called it, warbled,
وبالفعل، غنت، أو كما يسمي ذلك دِيرِيكْ، غردة،
to him for his first few years of life.
له منذ نعومة أظفاره.
And I think it was that excitement with hearing her voice
وأعتقد أن حماسه لسماع صوتها
hour after hour every day that made him think
لساعات طوال كل يوم جعلها تعتقد
maybe, you know, in his brain something was stirring,
بأنه ربما يكون قد حرك لديه شيء ما،
some sort of musical gift.
كموهبة موسيقية مثلا.
Here's a little picture of Derek going up now,
هذه صورة لدِيرِيكْ وقد كبر قليلا،
when you were with your nanny.
عندما كُنْتَ برفقة حاضنتك.
Now Nanny's great other insight was to think,
بعدها فكرت الحاضنة بشيء أخر عظيم،
perhaps we should get Derek something to play,
لربما علينا أن نقدم لدِيرِيكْ آلة موسيقية ليلعب بها،
and sure enough, she dragged this little keyboard
وبالفعل، قامت بإحضار هذا البيانو الصغير
out of the loft, never thinking really
من العلية، ولم يخطر ببالها أبدا
that anything much would come of it.
أن ذلك قد يأتي بنتيجة ما.
But Derek, your tiny hand must have gone out to that thing
لكن على الأرجح يا دِيرِيك أن يديك الصغيرتين أمسكتا بذلك البيانو
and actually bashed it,
وبدأت بالنقر عليه بشدة،
bashed it so hard they thought it was going to break.
بالنقر عليه بشدة حتى اعتقدوا بأنه سيتحطم.
But out of all the bashing, after a few months,
لكن بعد النقر عليه لعدة أشهر،
emerged the most fantastic music,
برزت الموسيقى الرائعة،
and I think there was just a miracle moment, really, Derek,
وأظن أنها كانت لحظة إعجاز، أليس كذلك دِيرِيك،
when you realized that all the sounds you hear in the world
عندما أدركت بأن من بين كل تلك الأصوات التي تسمعها من حولك
out there is something that you can copy on the keyboard.
هناك بعض الأصوات التي يمكن تقليدها بواسطة البيانو.
That was the great eureka moment.
كانت تلك لحظة اكتشاف.
Now, not being able to see meant, of course,
وبالطبع، أن يكون الإنسان ضريرا يعني
that you taught yourself.
بأنه عليه أن يعلم نفسه بنفسه.
Derek Paravicini: I taught myself to play.
دِيرِيك بافيتشيني: تعلمت العزف لوحدي.
AO: You did teach yourself to play,
أدم: تعلمت العزف بنفسك،
and as a consequence,
ونتيجة لذلك،
playing the piano for you, Derek,
فإن العزف على البيانو، كان بالنسبة لك يا دِيرِيك،
was a lot of knuckles and karate chops,
مجرد لَكْم وكاراتيه،
and even a bit of nose going on in there.
بل حتى استخدام الأنف كان مسموحا به.
And now, here's what Nanny did also do
فجاءت الحاضنة بفكرة أخرى هي
was to press the record button on one of those little
تسجيل كل ما يعزفه بواسطة المسجل القديم
early tape recorders that they had,
الذي كان لديهم في ذلك الوقت،
and this is a wonderful tape, now, of Derek playing
وهذا تسجيل رائع لدِيرِيك وهو يعزف
when you were four years old.
عندما كنت في عمر الرابعة.
DP: "Molly Malone (Cockles and Mussels)."
دِيرِيك: "مُولِي مَالُون (كُوكْلِسْ أند مُوسِلْس)."
AO: It wasn't actually "Cockles and Mussels."
أدم: "في الحقيقة لم تكن "كُوكْلِسْ أند مُوسِلْس."
This one is "English Country Garden."
فهذه كانت "حديقة عامة إنجليزية."
DP: "English Country Garden."
دِيرِيك: "حديقة عامة إنجليزية."
(Music: "English Country Garden")
(موسيقى: "حديقة عامة إنجليزية")
AO: There you are.
أدم: كان هذا هو المقطع.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I think that's just fantastic.
أظن أنه لا يسعني سوى القول بأن هذا مدهش.
You know, there's this little child who can't see,
لدينا طفل صغير ضرير،
can't really understand much about the world,
غير قادر على فهم ما يجري من حوله بالشكل اللازم،
has no one in the family who plays an instrument,
ولا يوجد بأسرته عازف موسيقى،
and yet he taught himself to play that.
ومع ذلك علم نفسه كيف يعزف تلك المقطوعة.
And as you can see from the picture,
وكما تلاحظون بالصورة،
there was quite a lot of body action going on
كان جسمك يتحرك كثيرا
while you were playing, Derek.
أثناء عزفك، صحيح دِيرِيك،
Now, along -- Derek and I met when he was four and a half years old,
تعرفت على دِيرِيك عندما كان في عمره 4 سنوات ونصف،
and at first, Derek, I thought you were mad, to be honest,
وبصراحة دِيرِيك، اعتقدت في البداية أنك مجنون،
because when you played the piano,
لأنك كنت عندما تعزف على البيانو،
you seemed to want to play every single note on the keyboard,
تبدو كمن يريد الضغط على جميع مفاتيحه،
and also you had this little habit
بالإضافة إلى العادة التي كانت لديك
of hitting me out of the way.
في ضربي كي تبعدني.
So as soon as I tried to get near the piano,
بحيث كلما حاولت الإقتراب من البيانو،
I was firmly shoved off.
كنت تبعدني بحزم.
And having said to your dad, Nic,
وبما أني أخبرت والدك، نِيك،
that I would try to teach you, I was then slightly confused
بأني أرغب بمحاولة تعليمك العزف، بدأت أرتبك
as to how I might go about that
بشأن الطريقة التي يمكنني بها تعليمك
if I wasn't allowed near the piano.
إن لم يكن مسموحا لي حتى أن أقترب من البيانو.
But after a while, I thought, well, the only way
لكن وبعد مدة، فكرت في أن الطريقة الوحيدة
is to just pick you up, shove Derek over to the other side of the room,
هي بحملك ووضعك في الجهة الأخرى من الغرفة،
and in the 10 seconds that I got before Derek came back,
لأعزف خلال العشر ثوان التي يستغرقها للعودة لمكانه،
I could just play something very quickly
لم يكن أمامي خيار سوى أن أعزف له
for him to learn.
شيئا سريعا للتعلم.
And in the end, Derek, I think you agreed
وفي النهاية، أعتقد بأنك توافقني الرأي يا دِيرِيك،
that we could actually have some fun playing the piano together.
بأننا حظينا ببعض المرح بالعزف على البيانو معا.
As you can see, there's me in my early,
وكما تلاحظون بالصورة، هذا أنا في عز شبابي،
pre-marriage days with a brown beard,
بلحية بُنِّية اللون، أيام ما قبل الزواج،
and little Derek concentrating there.
ودِيرِيك الصغير وهو مُرَكِّز.
I just realized this is going to be recorded, isn't it? Right. Okay.
أدركت للتو بأن هذا العرض سيسجل، أليس كذلك؟ سأبحث عن هدية لزوجتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now then, by the age of 10, Derek really
في سن العاشرة أصبح دِيرِيك
had taken the world by storm.
أشهر من نار على علم.
This is a photo of you, Derek, playing at the Barbican
هذه صورة لك يا دِيرِيك وأنت تعزف بمركز بَارْبِيكَانْ
with the Royal Philharmonic Pops.
رفقت الأوركيسترا الفيلارمونية الملكية بوبس.
Basically it was just an exciting journey, really.
الحقيقة أنها كانت رحلة مثيرة حقا،
And in those days, Derek, you didn't speak very much,
وكُنْتَ في تلك الأيام لا تتكلم كثيرا، يا دِيرِيك،
and so there was always a moment of tension
وكانت دائما هناك لحظة توتر
as to whether you'd actually understood what it was we were going to play
بشأن ما إذا كنت فهمت أي مقطوعة سنعزف
and whether you'd play the right piece in the right key,
وما إذا كنت ستعزف المقطوعة الصحيحة بالمفتاح الصحيح،
and all that kind of thing.
وأشياء أخرى من هذا القبيل.
But the orchestra were wowed as well,
لكن الأوركسترا وكل صحافة العالم
and the press of the world were fascinated by your ability
كانت منبهرة بقدرتك
to play these fantastic pieces.
على عزف تلك المقطوعات الرائعة.
Now the question is, how do you do it, Derek?
لكن السؤال الأن، كيف فعلت ذلك دِيرِيك؟
And hopefully we can show the audience now
هذا ما سنريه الأن للحضور
how it is you do what you do.
كيف يمكن لشخص مثلك القيام بذلك.
I think that one of the first things that happened
أعتقد بأن أول الأمور حدثت
when you were very little, Derek,
عندما كنت لاتزال صغيرا يا دِيرِيك،
was that by the time you were two,
كان ذلك عندما كنت في سن الثانية،
your musical ear had already outstripped that of most adults.
مقارنة بمعظم الراشدين كانت أذنك الموسيقية أكثر تطورا.
And so whenever you heard any note at all --
وهكذا كلما سمعت أي نغمة موسيقية--
if I just play a random note --
كأن أعزف نغمة بشكل عشوائي--
(Piano notes) --
(نغمات البيانو)--
you knew instantly what it was,
كنت فورا تتعرف عليها،
and you'd got the ability as well to find that note on the piano.
وكانت لديك القدرة على إيجاد تلك النغمة على البيانو.
Now that's called perfect pitch,
وهذا ما يدعى بالأذن المُرْهَفَة،
and some people have perfect pitch for a few white notes
بعض الأشخاص لديهم أذن مرهفة لبعض النغمات البيضاء
in the middle of the piano.
التي تقع بمنتصف مفاتيح البيانو.
(Piano notes)
(نغمات البيانو)
You can see how -- you get a sense of playing with Derek.
يمكنكم أن تلاحظوا كيف -- أنكم تحسون بمتعة العزف مع دِيرِيك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But Derek, your ear is so much more than that.
لكن أذنك،يا دِيرِيك، هي أكثر من ذلك.
If I just put the microphone down for a bit,
سأضع الميكوفون جانبا للحظة،
I'm going to play a cluster of notes.
سأعزف بعض النغمات.
Those of you who can see will know how many notes,
أنتم كأشخاص قادرين على الرؤية ستعرفون كم من نغمة عزفت،
but Derek, of course, can't.
لكن وبالطبع دِيرِيك لا يستطيع.
Not only can you say how many notes,
بالرغم من هذا أنت لا تقوم فقط بتحديد عدد النغمات،
it's being able to play them all at the same time. Here we are.
بل تستطيع عزفها جميعها بنفس الوقت. فلنبدأ.
(Chords)
(تآلف النغمات)
Well, forget the terminology, Derek. Fantastic.
لا تهتم بالمصطلحات دِيرِيك. المدهش هو
And it's that ability, that ability to hear simultaneous sounds,
تلك القدرة على الاستماع لمجموعة من الأصوات في نفس الوقت،
not only just single sounds, but when a whole orchestra is playing,
وليس لأصوات منفردة، فعندما تعزف كل الأوركسترا،
Derek, you can hear every note,
فإنك قادر على سماع كل نغمة، صحيح دِيرِيك،
and instantly, through all those hours and hours of practice,
وعلى الفور، بفضل ساعات وساعات من التدريب،
reproduce those on the keyboard,
تعزف تلك النغمات على مفاتيح البيانو،
that makes you, I think, is the basis of all your ability.
وأعتقد، أن هذا ما يشكل أساس كل قدراتك.
Now then.
الأن قد تتساءلون.
It's no use having that kind of raw ability
ما فائدة امتلاك مثل هذه الموهبة
without the technique,
دون التقنية اللازمة للاستفادة منها،
and luckily, Derek, you decided that,
ولحسن الحظ يا دِيرِيك، قررت
once we did start learning, you'd let me help you
بمجرد أن بدأنا في التعلم، بأن تتركني أساعدك
learn all the scale fingerings.
في تعلم كل شيء حول استخدام الأصابع.
So for example using your thumb under with C major.
كتمرير إبهامك أسفل مقام دو الكبير.
(Piano notes)
(نغمات البيانو)
Etc.
إلخ.
And in the end, you got so quick,
وفي النهاية، أصبحت سريعا بما يكفي،
that things like "Flight of the Bumblebee"
لعزف مقطوعة مثل "طيران الدبور"
were no problem, were they?
دون مشاكل، أليس كذلك؟
DP: No.
دِيرِيك: لا.
AO: Right. So here, by the age of 11,
أدم: حسنا. وفي سن 11،
Derek was playing things like this.
أصبح دِيرِيك قادرا على عزف مقطوعات مثل هذه.
DP: This.
دِيرِيك: هذه.
(Music: "Flight of the Bumblebee")
(موسيقى: "طيران الدبور")
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
AO: Derek, let's have a bow.
أدم: دِيرِيك، لِنُحَيِّ الجمهور.
Well done.
أحسنت.
Now the truly amazing thing was, with all those scales, Derek,
الشيء المدهش بالفعل، أنه رغم كل تلك السلالم الموسيقية،
you could not only play "Flight of the Bumblebee"
فإنك لم تتمكن فقط من عزف "طيران الدبور"
in the usual key, but any note I play,
بالشكل الصحييح، بل تمكن دِيرِيك من عزفها،
Derek can play it on.
على أي نغمة أختارها أنا.
So if I just choose a note at random, like that one.
إذا اخترت مثلا نغمة بشكل عشوائي، كهذه.
(Piano notes)
(نغمات البيانو)
Can you play "Flight of the Bumblebee" on that note?
هل يمكنك عزف "طيران الدبور" على هذه النغمة؟
DP: "Flight of the Bumblebee" on that note.
دِيرِيك: "طيران الدبور" على هذه النغمة.
(Music: "Flight of the Bumblebee")
(موسيقى:"طيران الدبور")
AO: Or another one? How about in G minor?
أدم: أو على النغمة أخرى؟ ماذا عن صُولْ المَخْفُوضَة؟
DP: G minor.
دِيرِيك: صُولْ المَخْفُوضَة.
(Music: "Flight of the Bumblebee")
(موسيقى: "طيران الدبور")
AO: Fantastic. Well done, Derek.
أدم: مدهش. أحسنت دِيرِيك.
So you see, in your brain, Derek, is this amazing musical computer
يحتوي دماغك يا دِيرِيك على حاسوب موسيقي مدهش
that can instantly recalibrate, recalculate,
قادر على تقويم وحساب كل المقطوعات بالعالم
all the pieces in the world that are out there.
بشكل فوري.
Most pianists would have a heart attack if you said,
معظم عازفي البيانو قد يصابون بنوبة قلبية إن قيل لهم،
"Sorry, do you mind playing 'Flight of the Bumblebee'
"من فضلك، هَلَّا عزفت "طيران الدبور"
in B minor instead of A minor?" as we went on.
على نغمة سي المخفوضة بدلا من لا المخفوضة.
In fact, the first time, Derek, you played that with an orchestra,
الحقيقة، أنك يا دِيرِيك، عندما عزفتها مع أوركسترا للمرة الأولى،
you'd learned the version that you'd learned,
كنت قد تدربت على النسخة المعروفة،
and then the orchestra, in fact, did have a different version,
بينما كان لدى الأوركسترا نسخة مختلفة،
so while we were waiting in the two hours
لدى خلال ساعتي الإنتظار
before the rehearsal and the concert,
قبل بداية فترة التدريب والحفل،
Derek listened to the different version and learned it quickly
استمع دِيرِيك للنسخة الأخرى وحفظها بسرعة
and then was able to play it with the orchestra.
ليتمكن بعدها من عزفها مع الأوركسترا.
Fantastic chap.
قدرة مدهشة.
The other wonderful thing about you is memory.
ثاني أروع شيء فيك هو الذاكرة.
DP: Memory. AO: Your memory is truly amazing, and every concert we do,
دِيرِيك: الذاكرة. أدم: ذاكرتك مدهشة بالفعل، ففي كل حفل نحييه،
we ask the audience to participate, of course,
نطلب من الجمهور المشاركة،
by suggesting a piece Derek might like to play.
بأن يقترح عزف مقطوعة على دِيرِيك.
And people say, "Well, that's terribly brave
ويقول الناس، "بأن دِيرِيك شجاع
because what happens if Derek doesn't know it?"
لأنه ما الذي سيحدث إن لم يكن يعرف المقطوعة؟"
And I say, "No, it's not brave at all,
وأجيب، "لا، تلك ليست شجاعة البَتَّةَ،
because if you ask for something that Derek doesn't know,
لأنه إن أنتم طلبتم مقطوعة لا يعرفها،
you're invited to come and sing it first,
سندعوكم للمنصة لكي تغنوها أولا،
and then he'll pick it up." (Laughter)
ليقوم هو بعدها بعزفها." (ضحك)
So just be thoughtful before you suggest something too outlandish.
لدى فكروا جيدا قبل اقتراح شيء ما غريب.
But seriously, would anyone like to choose a piece?
فهل يود أحد اختيار مقطوعة ما؟
DP: Choose a piece. Choose, choose, would you like to choose? AO: Because it's quite dark. You'll just have to shout out.
دِيرِيك: اختر مقطوعة. اختر، اختر، هل تودون الاختيار؟ أدم: بما أن القاعة مظلمة، سأطلب منكم فقط الكلام بصوت مرتفع.
Would you like to hear me play?
هل ترغبون في سماعي أعزف؟
(Audience: "Theme of Paganini.")
(الحضور: "نغمة معادة لبَاغَانِينِي.")
AO: Paganini. DP: "The Theme of Paganini."
أدم: بَاغَانِينِي. دِيرِيك: "نغمة معادة لبَاغَانِينِي."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Music: "Theme of Paganini")
(موسيقى: "نغمة معادة لبَاغَانِينِي.")
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
AO: Well done.
أدم: أحسنت.
Derek's going to L.A. soon,
سيسافر دِيرِيك إلى لوس أنجلوس قريبا،
and it's a milestone, because it means that Derek and I
وهذا بمثابة تتويج لدِيرِيك ولي
will have spent over 100 hours on long-haul flights together,
مقابل أكثر من 100 ساعة قضيناها معا خلال رحلاتنا الطويلة،
which is quite interesting, isn't it Derek?
والتي كانت مليئة بالإثارة، أليس كذلك دِيرِيك؟
DP: Very interesting, Adam, yes. Long-haul flights. Yes.
دِيرِيك: نعم مثيرة جدا، يا أدم. رحلات طويلة.
AO: You may think 13 hours is a long time to keep talking,
أدم: قد تعتقدون بأن 13 ساعة من الكلام هو أمر شاق،
but Derek does it effortlessly. Now then.
لكن بالنسبة لدِيرِيك ذلك ليس بمرهق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But in America, they've coined this term,
في أمريكا صاغوا مصطلح،
"the human iPod" for Derek,
"الرجل الأي-باد" لدِيرِيك،
which I think is just missing the point, really,
والذي أعتقد في الحقيقة أنه جَانَبَ الصواب،
because Derek, you're so much more than an iPod.
لأنك يا دِيرِيك أكثر من أي-باد
You're a fantastic, creative musician,
أنت مدهش، موسيقي مبدع
and I think that was nowhere clearer to see, really,
وأعتقد بأنك برهنت على ذلك
than when we went to Slovenia,
عندما ذهبنا إلى سلوفينيا،
and someone -- in a longer concert we tend to get people joining in,
حيث قام شخص ما -- خلال حفل طويل شاركنا فيه الجمهور،
and this person, very, very nervously came onto the stage.
حيث صعد شخص وهو متوتر على المنصة.
DP: He played "Chopsticks." AO: And played "Chopsticks."
دِيرِيك: عزف "شوبستيكس." أدم: عزف "شوبستيكس."
AO: A bit like this. DP: Like this. Yes.
أدم: بهذا الشكل تقريبا. دِيرِيك: نعم. بهذا الشكل.
(Piano notes)
(نغمات البيانو)
AO: I should really get Derek's manager to come and play it.
أدم: ينبغي علي أن أطلب من مدير أعمال دِيرِيك عزفها.
He's sitting there.
إنه جالس هناك.
DP: Somebody played "Chopsticks" like this. AO: Just teasing, right? Here we go.
دِيرِيك: أحدهم عزف "شوبستيكس" بهذا الشكل. أدم: أنا أمزح فقط. ها قد بدأنا.
(Music: "Chopsticks")
(موسيقى: "شابستيكس")
DP: Let Derek play it.
دِيرِيك: فلندع دِيرِيك يعزفها.
AO: What did you do with it, Derek?
أدم: ما الذي فعلته بها يا دِيرِيك؟
DP: I got to improvise with it, Adam.
دِيرِيك: لقد ارتجلت فيها يا أدم.
AO: This is Derek the musician.
أدم: هذا هو دِيرِيك الموسيقي.
(Music: "Chopsticks" improvisation)
(موسيقى: "شابستيكس" مرتجلة)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Music) (Clapping)
(موسيقى) (تَصفِيق بِالأيدِي)
Keep up with Derek.
رافقوا دِيرِيك.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The TED people will kill me,
سيقتلني منظموا هذا العرض من تِيد،
but perhaps there's time for one encore.
لكني أرجو أن يكون هناك بعض الوقت لإعادة أخرى.
DP: For one encore. AO: One encore, yes.
دِيرِيك: إعادة أخرى. أدم: إعادة أخرى؟ نعم.
So this is one of Derek's heroes.
هذا واحد من أبطال دِيرِيك.
It's the great Art Tatum -- DP: Art Tatum.
الموسيقار العملاق أَرْ تَاتُومْ -- دِيرِيك: أَرْ تَاتُومْ.
AO: -- who also was a pianist who couldn't see,
أدم: الذي كان بدوره عازف بيانو ضرير،
and also, I think, like Derek,
والذي أعتقد كدِيرِيك،
thought that all the world was a piano,
كان بدوره يرى العالم من خلال البيانو،
so whenever Art Tatum plays something,
بحيث كلما عزف أَرْ تَاتُومْ شيئا،
it sounds like there's three pianos in the room.
كان يخيل إليكم وكأنه يوجد هناك 3 بيانوهات بالغرفة.
And here is Derek's take on Art Tatum's take on "Tiger Rag."
وأترككم مع عزف دِيرِيك لمقطوعة "تايغر راغ" لأَرْ تَاتُومْ.
DP: "Tiger Rag."
دِيرِيك: "تايغر راغ."
(Music: "Tiger Rag")
(موسيقى: "تايغر راغ")
(Applause)
(تصفيق)